welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
boom
alright check-ins I am feeling stoic in
a playful way mmm
and there's like a sensual element to
and in in a meta way so welcome to the
Stella the stoa is a place that's
stewarded by a stoic and I'm viewing it
as a digital campfire for us to cohere
in dialogue but what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment and today we
have Reece Lynn mark and I'm gonna read
about me on Reese's website hi my name
is Reese Lynn mark I'm a post VC who
helps frontier people manifest their
ideas around post capitalism meta
rationality and social technical systems
so basically my best friend so today
what we're gonna do is Reese is going to
share his thoughts on on the title of
today's talk ghovat to post capitalism
and he's gonna run us through a series
of exercises I'll let him explain it and
and do everything here so with that
being said I'll head over to Reese sweet
thank you Peter can everybody hear me
okay give me thumbs up okay sweet sunset
yeah nice hello everybody
ah how's it going we'll do some
check-ins some individual check-ins in a
second but thank you all for coming
today I'm drinking out of a very large
mug this mug is almost as big as my face
so that's impressive and again thank you
to Peter for hosting this space I think
it's really cool it's a cool space for
experimentation so that's what we're
gonna do today is do some
experimentation and so at a high level
what's gonna happen is let me actually
start to share my screen here so desktop
one beautiful um thumbs up can you see
my screen we got some thumbs okay sweet
and so hopefully you're in the right
place we're talking about post
capitalism today and how our humanities
responds to Co vid kind of
it and as a note for everybody this will
be about a little bit over an hour for
folks so hopefully you're able to say
the whole time and if not that's okay
too
as Peter noted my name is Rhys I used to
work at MIT teaching blockchain ethics
stuff and I have a cool podcast I'm
working on sinkhole bento ism which
we'll chat about later today and I self
taxed 10% of my income which is a fun
thing which we'll also talk about later
today
and today's the like overview of today
is we're gonna talk a little bit about
paradigms and how to make change within
a system and then we're gonna talk about
the specific these next for network ISM
coherent pluralism bento ism and
generosity is this like these four
pieces that kind of combined make up
this new mindset of its new paradigm
that I think we're going towards in the
future and so that's kind of the
high-level overview and as Peter
mentioned as well we're gonna do a lot
of each of these we'll have like a
little breakout room will be where we
will be able to chat with each other
about stuff so that would be fun um
before we do anything what I want to do
first is do some check-ins with each
other there are a lot of people install
from all over the place and so I think
it would be fun to just check in with
each other so I'm gonna make it make
some breakout rooms they're gonna be and
we're gonna take two minutes in those
rooms and what you just want do is you
shouldn't say hey you know who's who are
you how are you doing how are you really
doing and then also if you can say what
made you curious about this session and
on that note I actually want to um so
we're gonna have there's this beautiful
document which is a gonna be our
note-taking documents for today because
there's all these breakout rooms but you
all have lots of good ideas we want to
share and you know capture those ideas
in this Google Doc so I'm gonna share
this in the zoom now let me go to more
and then click chat and then click share
beautiful umm so everybody should click
on that link um and give me a thumbs up
once you've clicked on that link and are
in there
sweet so hopefully there's like once I
see I see about seven people in there I
see plus three plus four plus great so
click on that link get in there um and
so what we're gonna do in these breakout
rooms is you're just gonna say hi to
each other essentially and then also but
also answer what made you curious and
the idea is that as you are saying which
made you curious as you're sharing that
with each other kind of be typing those
into the the doc and say ah this is what
made me curious so that I both you're
sharing with your partner and that I
kind of know why you're here for future
reference and then one other note before
I break everybody on this breakout rooms
is that um stay in the session until the
timer ends so the way that these zoom
everybody's been zoom and a ton recently
and the way that they work is I'm gonna
click end breakout room and it's gonna
say you have 60 seconds you can click if
you want you can click the return to
session button do not do that wait the
full 60 seconds let it automatically
bring you back in that will give you the
full two minutes with the person so that
makes sense so it's gonna be it's gonna
say 60 seconds don't click on it wait
okay so with that just say hi to each
other we're going to go into these
breakout rooms for you know 120 seconds
two minutes and let me make the rooms
now choo-choo-choo okay welcome back
everybody I kind of love this because
everybody comes back and you can see
everybody's got smile and like
everybody's had like kind of a fun
conversation you could see all the 18
faces be cool there's some random other
people from the internet here right now
that's cool so thank you for doing that
I don't know if anybody took notes but
that's okay for the future yes people
who are typing that's awesome for the
future I definitely think that having
the notes will be helpful for me and for
you so let's talk about section one
right now this theory of paradigms so
the idea here and I have calls actually
the theory of change tool again let me
share my screen and sweet beautiful so
the idea here is the work that I mostly
do is around paradigm change and the
idea
is that if you have a lot of problems in
the world like climate change or
inequality or right now we have you know
covin 19 there's a lot of different
solutions that you can propose you could
try to change norms like for climate
change around playing fights if you're
trying to you know fight inequality you
can change the marginal tax rate or for
code my team you can't like fun vaccine
development there are a lot of different
options here and all the way that I
think about those that the highest
leverage option is what's called like
paradigm change or like mindset change
and this is from this great woman
Donella Meadows in her book 12 leverage
points or in a blog post on 12 leverage
points where she talked about how if you
want to change that a little you know
circle at the bottom left corner here
you can either do it by changing the
parameters which would be like changing
you know for the tax rate from 27
percent to 20 percent or whatever or you
could change the goals so you just
actually say oh that's actually change
the goals of the system or you can
change its more abstract and called the
paradigm and that has the highest amount
of leverage so as an example of this was
something like Facebook if you are in
Facebook and you think that there's
there's too much addiction on facebook
these days you could either change you
know some of a very small specific thing
like maybe in the uxu say hey do you
want to keep scrolling and now I don't
really want to keep scrolling right now
that's like a very small kind of
parameter base change or you could
change the goals of the system
so traditionally Facebook's main goal
was engagement which is like time on
site but then they changed it to be ah
let's change the goal would be time well
spent and when they changed to be time
well spent that then change the goals
the designers and everybody in Facebook
to be like oh maybe we don't want people
just be scrolling endlessly or whatever
or you go up even one level further and
go to something like social media as the
utility and say hey this is thinking of
it as a you know it's kind of a more of
a macro paradigmatic mindset change
around what is Facebook should Facebook
be a you know is it's just like a
company that is driven to connect people
or should we see it as you know a public
utility so that's an example of what I
mean by paradigm change and I want to
compare it to this thing by Lawrence
Leslie called his pathetic dot and this
has these four little it's these four
little things here that are point
this human the pathetic dot in the
middle and there are the kinds of
incentives and kind of hidden defaults
that can affect that person so with
markets you can affect somebody you can
incentivize things you can make laws you
could change some norms you could like
shame people for doing stuff or whatever
if you if we're not wearing the masks or
whatever or you can make some code and
those are all different ways to kind of
incentivize someone to do stuff to like
change behavior in the world and so I
like to think about this but where do
paradigms fit within this they exist
again one level above this so they are
the paradigm is these underlying
mindsets that then get manifest in the
laws in the markets in the norms or in
the code okay so it's not the code
itself it's not the norms of self it's
like one level abstracted another way I
think about this is with institutions so
you have religions or nation-states or
companies and again those things are
manifestations they manifest the
paradigm but they are not the paradigm
in in them itself um so when I when I
talk about post capitalism it's kind of
no one really knows what post capitalism
means everybody knows that Lacy's
capitalism is here with us but no one
really knows what's next and so when I
think about post capitalism I think that
some folks will talk about it as an
economic system i disagree with that i
think that post capitalism i think the
best way to frame it is as a mindset and
then that mindset will be manifest in
you know in its economic systems and
institutions and other things but really
thinking of it as a mindset is the best
way to process so we look later on the
line the rest of today's talk about how
post capitalism as a mindset is manifest
it's again it's not a specific economic
system
it's a paradigmatic or paradigm does
then being manifested a bunch of sub
things within society so with that let's
try some breakout rooms again so we're
gonna go into the rooms and this time
instead of two minutes are gonna have
three minutes and first you're gonna
just chaff the other person about like
you know check for understanding or
critiques you're gonna be like hey I
here's what I understood is this what
you understood is this what resis saying
maybe you'll like say I didn't really
get you here you can like type that into
the Google Doc or you can critique you
can be like I disagree with you I think
that this is a bad way to view this or
whatever
um if you want to here's this bonus
question which is to give a historical
example of how paradigm or mindset
change trickled down into the system so
again we're gonna break out into two
rooms with everybody and let me actually
let's do the same rooms for the first
half and then we're gonna switch rooms
for the actually no we're gonna you know
we're gonna recreate the rooms every
time that'll be that'll be more fun so
let's do that with this and again on the
Cova to on here you can see there's
paradigms is the next big section here
so as you start to type stuff maybe
choose to have one of you guys like the
the note-taker and to put those notes in
here and begin typing um so with that
let's take three minutes in these rooms
ready set go eat go into your rooms
see you in three minutes haiman so I
just say email you lost ho status I lost
it was hilarious accurate it was I'll
show you the image later but the I lost
who said this stuff so you can bring
people back I'll give it to you now so
did you were you able to bring people
back by the way I didn't do it yet I
just wanted to talk to you first to see
what your plan was that would be great I
think you should bring
oh sweet now I'm a thing I'm gonna say
close all rooms beautiful okay
is it possible to close all rooms click
quicker whatever that works folks who
were so I guess the side don't hear
Peter just for future reference is that
he is that I tried to join a room to
just was happening and in to be part of
the conversation and then when I tried
to do that it said you're no longer a
host anymore it then brought me back to
the main room alone and I was just
waiting yeah makes sense makes sense
cool that's good learning for a future
timers for all this yeah but that's
actually sad because it's fun to be able
to join the break it was just pop in and
out I Pro I wonder if I messed up well
that's we'll try that out a different
time maybe you have to be the owner of
the channel or something like that yeah
exactly
so welcome back everybody everybody else
will be here in about 5 4 3 2 1 so we'll
go there in a second okay hello
everybody and welcome back if you all
may not have noticed but I tried to that
was longer than three minutes and it was
also a sad user experience for me I
tried to join a breakout room to be like
what's happening in there and then it
kicked me out of that breakout room we
took away my host status and then just
put me alone in the middle room alone by
myself in the main room so and then I
had a message that's why you saw if
you're in the Google Doc you see me
writing hello everybody I'm alone so I'm
sorry about that but I hope that that
worked out okay and that discussion was
good um does anybody have let's try out
this yeah let's try more zoom features
today does anybody want to raise their
hand with any comments or questions from
from their session we'll just do kind of
one comment the raise hand button is
that I believe at the bottom um do you
all see it aha just sees it as in just
achar you raising your hand or are you
emoji hey nurse it's under reactions
thumbs up that's the reaction there yeah
I can't find a raise hands and they may
have taken it away in the most there's
you can clap or thumbs up in reactions
if you go where if you want a
participant at the bottom you can say
raise hand yes no beautiful beautiful
okay nice
oh sweet so someone did that just raise
your head okay just you have to do you
want to say anything from your session
any questions or comments or paradigms I
mean sure now that I have one um we came
up with a couple of possible shifts
about 1:00 the the shift in norm around
gay rights and the friend also the fall
of the Berlin Wall and then shifts we
were talking about the shifts relating
to theism and atheism throughout our
lifetimes but mostly I think we go to a
lake hmm it's actually really hard to
point out when the paradigm shift occur
and whether they're happening in yeah I
agree with that and the one thing I'd
add to that and especially one thing we
think about strategically here's the gay
rights one brings up there's a bunch of
different things that have changed in
our lifetimes whether it's gave right or
like medical marijuana or things like
that and when you look at the curves or
how much of those changes come as a
result of how much of the changes come
as a result of new people being born in
old people dying or as a result of
mindset changes it actually looks like
most of the changes are a result of like
the generational thing of old people
dying and new people being born which is
kind of sad because it makes it
untrackable the problem where you just
kind of need to wait for people to die
and for new people to be born but that's
just a note a lot of these paradigm
changes that they mostly happen just
your generation it's it's also unclear
whether something like gay rights is a
paradigm change because whether or not
gay people should be allowed to be
married is still a question that existed
within the previous paradigm it's like
if we charted a whole new paradigm what
Meredith marriage was and maybe that
would be a paradigm shift degree yeah I
agree
I think the takeaway for everybody here
is just that when we think about what
we're trying about today and as we
switching to post capitalism or Gabey or
whatever you want to call this thing
that's up next for society the it is
happening what we're gonna talk about is
mostly at that you know meta kind of
abstracted level so with that let's go
back to sharing the screen chat about
some specifics today so let me go back
over here button beautiful um and so
yeah so now chatting about each of these
four kind of sub buckets of network ISM
coherent pluralism bento ism and
generosity I know that there's a lot of
terms in there but uh I want to give a
brief overview of them before you die
so network ISM is just the idea that
we're moving from a centralized a lot of
these centralized trusted institutions
like banks and nation-states and
companies and things like that and we're
moving towards these distributed
networks bottom-up institutions and this
is mainly as a result of there being
four billion networks smartphones out
there where you can give and receive
information at zero marginal cost and
sort of seeing all these new networks
the second one is coherent pluralism and
the idea here is instead of being now
it's kind of a result it's kind of a
reaction to network ISM so when we live
in a sense making environment an
information environment of lots of
networks instead of just consuming radio
or TV you have to consume a lot of
fertile istic different sources and then
try to create coherence among them so
it's kind of like a responsible
individuals reaction to network ISM the
third one is called bento ISM and bento
ISM the idea here is that you have a
it's this little 2x2 and it's a it has
the ideas that we're moving from this
bottom left corner now me where you can
kind of zoom out from our now me
focusing just on me perspective and zoom
out for me to think about a future me to
think about you know now us and to think
about future us and climate change and
things like that
it's kind of thinking about our needs in
society and then the fourth one is
generosity and the generosity or
abundance and the idea here is that it's
kind of this shift where we recognize
bro now me perspective that some of us
have enough that we have enough and that
we can then give to future us and we can
give to others in the system so those
are kind of the four made the four key
pieces of this new mindset and I want to
talk about how each of them is embodied
in our response to kovat so if that was
tried about network ISM first and so as
a reminder this would network ISM it is
and you can see it in these funny
Twitter comments this these new
networked institutions where top left
like hey a $10 override is a lot cheaper
than $3,000 from an ambulance that was
after a result of people you know
calling ubers instead of to be taken to
the emergency room instead of ambulances
or this bottom left one it's like hey
how long until GoFundMe is our nation's
leading health
provider that's kind of funny but it's
also kind of sad it's also just true or
it's like it's a good way for us inside
like help or to go to help each other
out
by using this networked funding
mechanism for folks with health care and
then this final one it says what if
public infrastructure was funded by the
crowd
wow what a crazy idea that's like this
new networked idea where you you crowd
funds of any things and putting that
against or as some would call it taxes
like that's not a traditional
centralized way to fund public
infrastructure so these all kind of show
this move towards network ISM and I want
to talk about how our response to Co vid
embodies that so I'm gonna talk about
three different things here one is from
an information perspective two is from a
money perspective and three is from an
institutional perspective so from an
information perspective the the
centralized version of things here is
like main media or mainstream media
while the non centralized version is
networked influencers and I want to show
let's make this big again so on the
centralized side we saw it was kind of
interesting to see what happens here
there's this recent piece from recode
that says what went wrong with the
media's coronavirus coverage and can we
do better is kind of just like in 2016
when a bunch of folks were being like
whoa wow Trump got elected we're so
surprised and there were a lot of like
post-mortems after that and as you can
see here there's this like this image at
the bottom is just a bunch of like
mainstream media sites talking about
coronavirus and you know January
February March and just like dismissing
it essentially and the issue in this
article the main thing I won't have here
is that when journalists and media
sourced things they sourced stuff from
credentialed experts and institutions
which traditionally had been good but
actually if you're asking the CBC if you
should wear masks X amount of time ago
and they would still just say no no no
and so that was um one of the issues
with kind of like the centralized sense
making versus on the other side here you
have this new decent license making and
the idea here this graph is from this
graph is from strategy and the idea is
now that we have now that the marginal
cost is zero to copy and distribute
information all around the world
we just have a lot more information a
lot of information is in the middle
ground here with just like you know
average information some that
information is obviously bad it's
misinformation but some of that
information is super valuable and so
what happened is Twitter and other
universes what they did is they were
able to source the information and you
know the valuable information more
quickly kind of from first principles
through this kind of decent choice and
network on Twitter so you can kind of
see those two responses and sense-making
to something like the coronavirus here
that's on the infant information side on
the money side about this more with
generosity later and money there but
easy way to look at this is kind of
top-down stimulus versus bottom-up
network grants so the top-down stimulus
this is a some pseudocode I wrote for
the for the US stimulus package which is
two trillion dollars and essentially
it's a very top-down seeing like a state
perspective or just like hey for every
person give them $1,200 or you know
create $1,200 out of thin air and give
them if they are not employed give them
an extra $600 if you're a small medium
business that pays your staff you know
you can have a 10 million bucks for
every state give them three hundred
forty billion dollars son giving three
hundred forty billion dollars at
proportional to their population or
divided among populations
proportionately if your Hospital here's
100 million bucks airlines have fifty
eight billion and then put 450 billion
in the federal count that you can loan
out at 10x to anybody else that's kind
of like the seeing like a state top-down
money perspective and that's different
than you know this bottom-up perspective
which is like okay this thing called
fast grants which was fast funding for
science and they just got together
really quick they said hey here's ten
million bucks we'll get to you in 48
hours if you get it or don't get it get
the money and so just a much kind of
those kind of Institute's like a
bottom-up quick way to fund science that
we need so that's one way to look at
this the final way is from an
institutional perspective and what I
mean here is when you think about
institutions there are things that
coordinate and motivate people and the
coordination usually comes from
information and the motivation usually
comes from money so those two things
combined kind of make an institution and
on I want to show like some companies
that are centralized and then some
new networked orgs as some decentralized
examples so on the centralized side you
have something like 3m which makes masks
and it's free sweet they're making they
doubled their mass production the last
you know three to six months and now
they're moving up to 25 million masks
per week which is a lot and they're
obviously a very old company and that's
first is this kind of decentralized
response which is this thing called
open-source kovat medical supplies which
is just a random you know Facebook group
it has 70,000 people in it and they're
making a million masks per week which
you know is only is you know four
percent of what 3m is making but it was
they were they're actually increasing at
2x 2.5 x per week and they were founded
just recently and obviously I guess I
would I want to highlight here is that
they were also founded Facebook as the
thing barely existed ten years ago 3d
printing as a thing barely existed 10
years ago and so when you think about
these two these are two different
responses institutional responses here
and I think that obviously it's not the
case that open source code medical
medical supplies was it's difficult to
compare them and obviously the one on
the right is like worst quote unquote
but it's just new it's just an emerging
it's like a proto example what we're
starting to see here another one is this
masks for all movement so I asked folks
on Twitter hey did mask for actually
have an impact on the CDC's announcement
and I was like almost certainly it CDC
made a decision without thinking about
the hash tag or the movement but one of
the main leaders of mask sprawl actually
replied said yes it did I have
first-hand knowledge so he was like
actually master all was a pretty like
the hash that weirdly like the hash tag
itself was helpful in changing the CDC
decisions like that's weird right he
says you know by hash tag he means you
know many hours of pitching and briefing
politicians and their teams know similar
legwork so it's obviously not just like
CDC saw a hash tag was like sweet let's
make masks for all but the mask for all
movement was definitely a big part of
that shift so that's another example
there are other really interesting
things like hash tag get us PPE and get
us TPP which you know combined abundant
was a clearinghouse for a bunch of these
PPE marketplaces st. Corona fires tech
handbook was an amazing handbook that
was coming up at very
that just had permissions on for
everybody and anybody could add to it on
so again these bottom up responses to
this versus the top down so with that
you can see these as all from an
information perspective from a money
perspective or an institutional
perspective there's the kind of
traditional centralized response and
then there's the bottom-up networked
response and with that
yeah the network ISM more generally is
just this trend in these new
decentralized institutions out competing
not on everything but out competing on a
variety of facets some of these old and
centralized institutions so with that we
are going to go into our sessions into
our breakout rooms and I will make sure
not to mess it up this time by trying to
go into one so again let's say you know
two or three minutes here and discuss
again what do you think about this just
check for understanding or critique and
then this interesting question here's
you know if we've seen a bunch of these
hashtags show up hashtag is SPE hashtag
masks for all you know hash tag cloud
the curve what hashtags would you expect
to gain traction in the next 12 months
of CO vid that would that's like one way
to view this so with that hello
everybody and welcome back I hope you
chatted about network ISM we're gonna
zoom right into coherent pluralism now
um and so let me go back to sharing my
screen there's my time or beautiful
timing you know so the next one is
coherent Thurl ism and the idea behind
coherent pluralism is that it's kind of
the the correct response to a networked
environments to a network sense-making
environment so here's John Lennon with
some classes that CD you're kind of
putting on a bunch of these different
glasses in order to create a plural
perspective but still a coherent one I
just want to share this picture on the
right is from this piece that I'm
writing right now and I am having
someone illustrate it and that is how
she represented coherent plurals which
is cool so the idea here is that you
think of this from over the last couple
hundred years perspective where you had
this modernism's modernism thing which
is like hey here's the truth nationalism
and patriotism like broadcasting the
truth
top-down you know
broadcasting through the TV through
radio that perspective it's one one lens
then you have like this post-modernism
perspective for this fake news
perspective which is maybe I have my red
feed maybe I have my blue feed you know
what I don't really know what is true
I'm just gonna be super pluralistic and
I'm not there is no truth there's no
fake news what is even real and that's
not right either
and so what you want is this kind of
meta modernist perspective or that's
just another name for coherent pluralism
which is to have multiple different
glasses you're putting on to view things
in pluralistic way but then create
coherence among them um so again it's
how responsible individuals do since
making given network ISM and again
here's I kind of a way to think about it
is like if you think about that first
thing on the left you have me praying at
this point again on the left here you
have if you're just consuming from one
source and maybe you're consuming from
one of these sources then you might have
thought something about Co fit that was
just wrong or whatever but you also
can't do this middle perspective here
which is just like oh here's all this
information but not put these
misinformation and valuable information
things there's like there's so much
information whatever there's no truth
anymore everything's fake news and but
the third perspectives what you want to
have which has traits it's plural
perspective where you look at as many
things as you can and then create an
answer from that so when I kind of show
it in two big ways here with searching
for truth while existing and uncertainty
but then also through empathy
so the searching through for truth
existing uncertainty that's kind of the
vibe of coherent literalism it's like
this constant relentless search for the
truth while still things are pretty
uncertain so the example here is from
538 and I'm just gonna read this because
it really gets at this from a recent
post they had about masks and just
really gets at what it needs to be a
coherent plural individual so Maggie
writes ultimately the expert advice on
masks is to get comfortable with not
knowing the right answer you can and
should have some trusted advisors you
can and should read up on why certain
things are or are not being recommended
but there are a lot of issues around
this fire so much two experts can read
the same data and come to different
conclusions for the rest of us that just
means accepting that sometimes we'll
just have to do the best we can without
a clear set of instructions that's the
situation your your being coherent lis
plural your
having trust advisors and sources and
then you're just doing the best you can
that's what come here pluralism is like
the other version of coherent portal ISM
is this is there just um pluralistic
looking at like facts there's also like
a pluralist viewpoint was like empathy
other humans um and so this was this
great video that Italy put out ten days
before when they were in an intense
situation before the US was and so they
made this beautiful video where they
just went around and they said um where
it was just individuals on their phones
kind of stitched together saying these
these nice messages where's like hey
Danielle from ten days ago hey a huge
mess is about to happen you know we were
a two thousand there are eighteen
thousand I used to make fun of people
wearing face masks but now we're like a
whole nation stuck at home but there's
still good stuff like yesterday when we
got out on our balconies but really stay
at home like don't you know this is
serious stuff I thought this was a great
example of again an environment where
you can where everybody has smartphones
four billion networked smartphones you
can make information like this directly
from people's phones and we can really
empathize with these folks and for me
this is when most powerful pieces of of
this thing was seeing this addition to
me like wow that's what's gonna happen
to the US and other places around the
world that's really powerful so that's
what cohered pluralism is so again
within your groups let's have some folks
and I think that the again feel free to
you know check with each other on
questions and critique and then the
question here is how coherently plural
is your sense making right now could it
be more coherent akru just kind of like
existing in seas of information without
any coherence but could also be more
plural so maybe you don't have enough
sources or you're not looking from as
many perspectives as you should so with
that let's do this thing open up these
breakout rooms recreate um okay enjoy
your broom see in two minutes
that's actually we're gonna keep zooming
we got a we have nine more minutes left
so we're gonna keep zooming and
literally actually zooming so we're
going into the next one here which is a
bento ism so been to ism is a cool
concept and just as a note here
so is made by its from my friend Yancy
strickler's book this could be our
future and just for full disclosure I'm
like working with Nancy on this so I am
I'd like this more than maybe I should
but I think it's good and the idea is
that you have I like to think it from a
needs perspective where you have in the
bottom left corner here you have your
now me your basic needs you're like what
do I actually need right now any of your
future meat perspective which is stuff
like meaning so it's like meaning and
mastering and self-actualization it's
kind of your old self looking back then
you also have now us you're now it's
like connection and thinking about
others and you also have these futurist
needs of resilience and climate change
and things like that so it's just myself
to you by - and it's just a helpful way
to view the world and you can kind of
things you know not dissimilar from
mesos hierarchy um but I like it for a
variety of reasons but yeah the safety
and physiological ones are kind of like
now basic needs love and belonging use
kind of like connection
self-actualization is kind of like
meaning and then Maslow doesn't really
have this future rust piece so let's
talk about how our response to cope it
embodies been to ISM so we'll talk about
the bent of itself and just like how it
provides a nice view on what's happening
a way to view the world but also that
this the cofidis that we can actually do
a little bit of reflection on our needs
that we can go into what you know some
folks are calling quilts wartime
production mode so first from a bento
perspective itself from now meat
perspective you can see it's it's
happening I mean everybody did their now
meat thing initially like okay gotta go
to the grocery store get toilet paper
whatever um but also some really sad now
many things where it's like people
expect because of supply chain is using
these things like that about 800 million
people are hungry today but they're
expecting it to go up to a double to at
1.6 billion people would to be hungry as
a result of this that's the now meat
perspective the basic needs and then the
future me I think a lot of folks have
really felt this too or they're like
well like meaning in life this has
really changed like their directions and
things like that for where they want to
go and kind of like their laws of
adjacent possible what what is possible
for the future on the now us this is
really showing us how interconnected we
are this is just a graph of all the
places the the virus went at the
beginning and then from a futurist
perspective obviously stuff like you
know flattening the curve has really
made us be like okay I need to stay
inside now so that you know in a month
or two you know things aren't overloaded
with
and by within my city so that's that
perspective but I want I think the more
important thing here is actually just
like how the virus gives us a blank
slate and shows us that we can actually
change how we think about ourselves and
our humanity's needs so um you know
generally speaking we have exists on the
left side here if you know you know more
focused on now me and what this is kind
of doing is you know giving us this more
holistic perspective towards the more
general bento box so you can see this in
consumer spending um
this graph from New York Times about
just how you know spending going up and
down for various things but uh sit down
for variety of things where people are
responding to the event so they're kind
of changing their needs the other
example obviously is something here like
the total amount of tests we've had for
Coppa this is in the u.s. it's gone you
know now we're making made 3 million
total tests and this is again this is
like the wartime production side or the
plowshares two swords side where you've
taken these things that have normally
done a certain kind of thing for society
and you said hey let's actually change
them to be due to this other good thing
for society so I like to think of this
as a graph of the stock market and
obviously and it was going down and it's
gonna come back up and so it's gonna
look like a check mark on what timeline
we don't know but I like I think think
about as the check mark is not entirely
correct I think you have to think about
instead of just the X and the y-axis
here you could also think about the z
axis and the z axis is really what we're
talking about where the z axis the
question is how much is that z axis
going to be focused again on stuff like
you know our old way of doing things you
know this now me focus way of doing
things versus shifting towards more of
kind of a future us way of doing things
and whether or not do you agree with it
or don't agree with it the like green
new deal green stimulus is trying to get
at this idea and saying hey as we
rebuild and as we you know try to do
things differently going forwards how
come they could be you know more focused
on future us um as a funny example this
like you know my friend John on Facebook
was saying hey wow look at that rise in
covert 19 cases and things like oh wait
that's just global co2 never mind no
need to do anything I thought this was
funny and sad where it's just like
obviously for a lot of us we've seen
this with covent be like Oh God and now
we're doing at least intense measures
and obviously you have not
done that in society yet with stuff like
climate change we don't have those that
feedback tightly coupled enough yet so
yeah that's hope is that we moved
towards a box of bright more so again
been to ISM it's just it's a nice just
another a lens of viewing the world and
it really helps us understand humanity's
needs and that we can actually change
them and this crisis has showed us that
we can that during the crisis itself we
can change our needs we can go into
wartime production mode and hopefully
what it'll show us is that we can kind
of move towards more of these future us
facing perspectives as we kind of come
out of the crisis so with that we're
gonna go into some groups and I think
that what I want you to do is you know
ask the question how does your own bento
box respond to the question what should
I do in these Cobie times so you can ask
your own but I could say well my future
me self says this but my you know future
us self says this or whatever that's
kind of so you could gotta walk through
those different pieces um so with that
let's put you all into groups were
really grounded it just start naming the
arenas and the Freak
where are the breakdowns and what what
are the adjacent possible yeah yeah I
like that that was the meet us or the
now actually was future us that we were
into yeah that makes sense everybody we
were just chatting with Nancy for a hot
SEC about how they're talking about
Nancy saying how can you just break down
to break through and to think about
those laws of the jacent possible I'm so
we're gonna go into our final little bit
here um and then and then we're gonna
have a little bit of time dance either
you can leave when you want to leave or
we can chat about stuff for as long as
you want for I think there's a different
there's a there's a party afterwards so
we can't chat for infinity time but we
can chat for a bit so the final piece
here is generosity and so generosity the
idea generosity or abundance and the
idea here is that for for some of us and
I'm not I know a lot of folks for some
folks in the developed world we have now
me overflow which means that we kind of
have enough like for me right now I'm in
this nice room I have enough food
downstairs I have friends I have all
these great things in my life and so my
now
my basic needs are definitely filled up
my connection now I think they're almost
certainly filled up I get a lot of
meaning out of my work and so I could
really focus on giving my overflow just
like giving back money or whatever to to
now us into future us to help other
folks experience this as well so that's
the idea here and you can think of this
from a couple different perspectives one
there's this beautiful graph over the
last two centuries this top left one
especially look at that one it's extreme
poverty you know 200 years ago almost
everybody was in extreme poverty you
know 94 percent of people and now it's
less than 10% again that's still 750
million people which is crazy but so
much better than it used to be so we're
getting closer and close to that or like
child mortality you should be half a
kid's you should die before the age of
five now it's less than five percent
again like that's an amazing amazing
thing so we can kind of see it from this
macro perspective but also from the
micro perspective so this is a graph of
individual income on the log scale
versus how happy you get and of course
at the very beginning like if you're
almost you who live on less than $2 a
day but the first thousand dollars you
get is super super super impactful it
makes you a lot happier but then as you
keep on doing these dumplings it gets
you up a bit but then once you get to
forty five thousand dollars per year it
essentially doesn't make you happier you
essentially level out at that point and
so that's a very powerful perspective as
why is someone like me why I just self
tax myself ten percent because I'm like
look I got enough it doesn't the money's
not making you happier it actually makes
me happier to give it back to other
people which is great praise II and so
another key example this from a macro
perspective just something like
universal basic income if you think 200
years ago would have been possible to
give everybody basic income when kids
were still done when half kids are still
but dying before the age of five no much
more difficult but now it's actually a
possibility because we were having this
abundance of capital where we actually
can give back to the system so I want to
show it so that's the idea behind it but
it shows up in three big ways with our
response one is these hashtags to us
like these mutual aid funds and three is
these billionaire philanthropy things so
these hashtags the idea here is just to
let the money flow through you there's
this one hashtag past the check from
give directly and this other one split
the check again there's a hashtag I
don't know where the hashtag is in here
and thus far the idea is that when you
get your check from the government you
$1,200 you just
give it to someone else you pledge to to
let it pass through you and pass it on
to someone else and roughly right now
forgive directly about a thousand people
have pledged to pass on the check for a
total of a million dollars that's not
very much in the big scheme of things
but again similar to the things were
chatting about earlier with the masks
and 3m stuff um we didn't even see this
very much during 2008 and 2008 financial
crisis I mean hashtags hadn't were just
invented 2007 at that time so it's like
again these are proto examples of like
the government you know doing helicopter
money you know feeding us with money and
then people reckon I think I can just
let it flow through me back to the
system that's one example
another is adding money to these shared
pools so the idea here is that you just
kind of have if you have bonus money you
can just kind of put it in the shared
pool and let people take from it so
these are all there's this huge
explosion of mutual aid documents that
showed up after as kovat started and
these are just some notes of people and
say hey um I convened oh four different
parties $50 each for supplies PM me you
know or I hate this someone says hey
convened owe you 40 bucks this is the
first essay I convened in my you 50
bucks to get groceries these are just a
button this and these are obviously just
for exams there's so many people are
speaking like look I got bonus money who
needs it and so just putting into the
shared pool and then trust and allowing
anybody else to take that money from the
pool this is obviously also happened
with things like GoFundMe just kind of a
institutionalized or codified version of
this where you have these big pools of
people you know raising for America's
food fund this is you know 14 million
bucks across you know 10,000 plus donors
or this like frontline responders fund
which is you know 7 million bucks across
almost 20 thousand donors so people
being like look I got enough I can help
out and I can give back to the system
why don't make one final note on this
which is kind of a weird one which is
that I'm all into the self taxing thing
and giving back in a weird Friday race
and so I was on Craigslist
a year or two ago I just put up on there
I said hey I have 300 20 bucks cash
anybody want this and when I did that at
the time and I was like talking about
with friends and went from the internet
like people thought it was just weird
they thought it was like really weird um
and it obviously is kind of weird but
also now that this coke thing has
happened all these things are the exact
same example this it's people just
offering opting look I have this money
does anybody want it and so now it just
seems a little bit more normalized
they're just kind of cool
that's the second big piece is adding
money to shared pools and the third big
piece is billionaire from the entropy
this one this gets into the weirdness of
like abundance versus generosity like
how generous am I personally really be
eating if I live if I'm a rich white man
straight man who lives in America who
you know it's a college house computer
science degree and clearly have
abundance like am I really being
generous or is it just like me giving
what I already but I didn't really earn
or whatever back the system any case you
can see some examples this I think the
best one is someone like Jack Dorsey
really giving I mean 20 percent of his
wealth is a lot of his wealth I'm into
this fund and he just puts it in it's
also funny again back to the like bottom
up this he just has a Google spreadsheet
where he says here's how much money I'm
giving two different things so that's
the final piece of this abundance thing
so that's it here we're actually not
going to go into these breakout rooms
but I just want to go into conclusion
mode to say again so the what was what
we're mostly talking about here is this
paradigm change which we're not just
like tweaking some little parameters
we're not even changing goals we're
changing that we're trying to change
these macro ideas of how institutions
are formed and what money means and
other people have enough and whether you
need to you know you know hoard it all
for yourself or that we're trying to
change stuff at the paradigm level well
then trickle down into laws and markets
and code and all those kinds of things
and here are these four big key ideas
that do it and I want to actually make
one found out here which is actually
Peter and I were chatting about this but
when I was when we were discussing what
I should talk about it was like four IDs
is kind of too many like it's a lot of
ideas but they actually are interlocking
and an interesting way and that like
network ism is this move towards
decentralized networks coherent
pluralism is like the response to that
like you have to be coherently plural
given a decent choice since making
environment or something like bento ism
is an example of coherent pluralism its
pluralistic and that's like it's this
two by two but it's also very coherent
and clear what it is and of course
generosity is can be expressed as
now--my overflow claim so they're kind
of an express in each others and
obviously with generosity we saw lots of
different like networks generosity where
it's not like people are you know the
fact that people could just put on a
random Google Doc spreadsheet hey
anybody can have this venmo money that's
an example of this network spot
about generosity - all these are being
kind of embodied in both existing
institutions but also these new
bottom-up networked institutions so
that's the macro idea here and I guess
what I would say is so a let me actually
share someone asked for this let me put
it in the chat I'll share this um yeah
remind me later I don't care about that
um this is the let me share this now I
actually put in chat this is the
spreadsheet or this is the Google Doc
from today so you can check that out if
you want to let's admit Bert
and then the other note is if you want
to learn more about this stuff you can
go to just like Risa Murr calm and
there's I curate a lot of these
movements in my new center so that's a
good place to check it out you can also
go to the bento ism bento some has a sub
stack and newsletter so that one is
specific to bento is and it has a lot of
great ideas for how to incorporate bento
ism like a weekly bento into your daily
life feel free to just hit me up if you
have any ideas or discussion or chronic
comments or critique or if you want to
help out we have some interesting new
research positions especially around
trying to see how these things are
manifest within Kovan and how we can
kind of find a path going for us to make
sure that we decide you look something
kind of like this new paradigm instead
of something that's rejecting that um so
with that thank you all again for coming
I think we can take let's take six
minutes for any final questions or
anything like that and then and then all
that Peter is you know talk about what's
next that kind of thing so does anybody
feel free to let's use the raise a hand
thing again does anybody if you click on
your Manito boom nice worth Keith you
got first um so Keith uh you can yeah I
speak yeah so um I think the main thing
when I read your newsletter recently and
invited a whole bunch people this call
was how impressed I was at the way that
you were making sense of things and also
the kind of rapidity of
your sense making response and I've been
writing my own paper on how this can be
like this moment can be an inflection
point for handling at essential risk
issues but I was wondering if you could
speak to how you are engaging with
making sense of things but kind of what
your own stack is there and then also
how that might relate to collective
intelligence how you're organizing when
feeding off other people's ideas and how
you kind of maintain those connections
yeah good question so and thank you for
and it's also funny because they had the
rapidity or the like the circular nature
of it is kind of annoying but kind of
true and I think it's crucial part of it
so I think that the wait and let me say
one thing also I guess if you notice
essential risks I just want to put a
quick plug for if you go to my website
and go to my about me there's like a
hundred page book on Mehta existential
risks so if you want to look at that if
you're into how exponential curves are
happening within AI nuclear security
biosecurity and climate change and how
to like meta solve them that's IDIA but
hopefully the meta solve is what we're
talking about today on your note of how
I do my own sense making hmm so I think
that it's weird I mean so for me
personally there's these crucial
networks of Facebook and Twitter and
those are things where you have to just
it's really a coherent leap or
perspective you're like okay who exists
you know keeping your Twitter feed and
really think about who you're following
and making sure you're following people
who you think are providing interesting
good information but also noticing your
own beacon so it takes a lot of self
understanding here various folks on this
call may be lawyers or developers or
whatever and so it's like knowing who
you are and then knowing that searching
for other similar people who are like
that and then putting out your beacon
out there I mean I look I'm a person
who's like this and then when you say
that's another people like oh me too
cool and then you start to just kind of
combine around like like a snowball kind
of so that's one thing I'd say is within
Twitter and Facebook make sure you're
following in the right people and trying
to know yourself and engage with those
people who are similar issue you then I
would say that there's a also the sub
stack at various newsletters so there's
a bunch of random newsletters that I
follow and I could put it on my website
sometime later but they're just like
crucial
just like they're a bunch of random
different newsletters about shareholder
capitalism and you know future tech VC
stuff so I not a clear answer there but
um newsletters is the other crucial
piece and then the collective
intelligence piece actually weird
because I think there's um how one
connects with others in this ecosystem
if I was operating in an old-school
environment in a gaming world then I
would like create a nonprofit and just
like start rocking and roll in there
versus in this new world it's like ah
should I create a hashtag or something
like that I'm like how should I operate
in that forum how much should I raise
should I try to make money so those are
like weirder questions I think are
harder to answer but when I do that I
try to just be in alignment with that
two by two so I try to do things in a
network first mode I try to do things in
a in a bent owest way I try to do things
in a coherently plural way and I try to
do things in a Nami overflow abundance
kind of way so that's my initial
response thank you for the question hope
that was helpful
um the other person who raised their
hand which I can look at here who trying
to guess okay just so the question I had
was something around uh what okay if you
imagine it's two or three years from now
and Kovac crisis has been and gone and
we're kind of back to like shitty normal
what why would that like what would have
been the cause of that like if we didn't
manage to put in any sort of like been
to his principles that would no paradigm
shift that happened we went back to kind
of this really uncomfortable capitalism
that everybody hates like what why would
that have happened like what's yeah yeah
that's good question I think that well I
think that's most likely to happen like
that's all these things are just Pro to
examples we're just in the beginning
stage here we're starting to make these
balls of people who are into these
things and again there's gonna be
there's eight billion people on earth
and and we're even if you think about
all those people and you think about it
still so 750 million I'm sort of making
less than two dollars a day it's like
they need to focus on their current
scarcity stuff and it's that's really
intense and sad and I think so yeah this
is gonna be we talk about this a lot of
like
not a 10-year startup plan it is a
generational shift so in the next three
years I pretty much expect things to go
as as normal to go back but I think that
what will happen in a negative sense is
hmm
I think that some of the things are like
what will have gone wrong I think that
many of the things that will have gone
wrong there are starting to see are just
like the classic
tough things are those like nation seats
are doing things that may not be the
best like you know the government has
their 454 billion dollars of money that
they put in the Federal Reserve this is
gonna lend that they can limit at ten to
one rate but they're not being
transparent about it right now
and so it's like are we just gonna do
some kind of thing or just like giving
money backs like random rich people who
have the amount of my to do lot it's
like that could be sad and true so I
think that that very well is it may
happen I thought maybe one way of asking
this is like what are the opportunities
that exists like roughly in this moment
good like what are the folks in the road
that we have right now that like without
taking them yeah yeah I think the forks
that we have now are hmm I think a big
Fork
is something like what does the now that
we've created you know Ray Dalio the
bridge water guy British water
billionaires talk about okay we've just
made a bunch of money how are we gonna
repay that debt and I think that the way
that we think about who repays that debt
and how and making sure that as we start
to replay that and we make things and
again I'm not like fully bullish on
green New Deal stuff but making more
green New Deal adjacent you know like
that that we're you know moving things
more towards this climate change you
future us inequality or equality based
perspective I think would be really
powerful so one fork is how much does
and again this is something that's hard
for all of us individually here on the
call to change but it's like from a
nation-state perspective how do those
laws get implemented I think the other
Forks just for us to know individually
or like maybe the forks are just things
like being with each other in groups um
and these new weird sense making groups
and just and I think that maybe Peters
this is a perfect example this is
something like the Stowe up or it's like
Peter had a fork in the road for himself
he knew that he could be like a glue
sense maker type and
Stewart a space like this and he decided
to do it and it's not like these 20
people on the call over and I couldn't
like change the world or ever we're
still just part of this massive movement
but I think that there's a sense in
which making seeing this time as an
opportunity to connect with an
experiment with these new forms of being
with the other aligned people I think
that's the primary fork in the road that
I see for us now for us to be like yeah
I am and you hop on that weird call with
those weird people are oh I'm gonna try
things in this weird new way that's I
think what I would probably say so let's
do one final question Peter if that's
okay and then we'll okay and then we can
leave so I'm sure it's better doing this
but Colin do you have a question so go
for it
yeah no just some thoughts out of what
you're just saying that sparked up for
me is one you're talking about the
possible troubles over the next few
years coming out of this and I mean one
of my big feels that I've been thinking
about is kind of the shifts in my
politics and James out of there's much
the way that like security changed after
9/11 how are we going to think of health
and wellness and also flus of people
goods it said about how all institutions
going to control how we live differently
now because of us so that's a big
question for me and then out of this
what you were just saying about new ways
of connecting etc thinking about the
decentering of normal and how what ways
can we you told these features that we
want and also how do we go about
questioning what do we want collectively
you see that last piece of it more time
Adi centering of normal and your in your
your think about how do we come se more
on that piece and how do we come to the
conclusion of what we want maybe not a
single conclusion but thinking about for
already rather than in the information
sense but in the
political sense how do we find new goals
thinking about these paradigms as will
move towards that instead of we're going
back to normal how are we thinking about
how do we build new goals that take new
networks etc so just to be more thoughts
on baddest interesting and of course the
infrastructures that loops back into
yeah so Nancy did you want to respond
yet a quick response that we're just
we've been given the opportunity to see
more clearly the needs and the different
ways of meeting the needs and in
addition to distilling from that
abstractions and models and structures
for sense making is to greatly enrich
the stories the proofs of concept of
different ways of doing things that are
emerging all over the world in response
to the breakdowns and the opportunities
and then reverse-engineer because part
of how we discover what we really really
want is to see something that we never
thought of I think of what's going on in
Taiwan Taiwan's version of democracy
right now
like who knew just who knew but what do
you see it's oh my god yeah that like
makes sense and there's those sorts of
examples at all levels of society and
all sectors and branches of the needs
these discoveries of how we actually can
meet our needs by healing and not
harming the planet or the people and
then reflecting on sharing those stories
not only raises our hope and our energy
and our sense of possibility but it
actually grounds it with a sense of
direction because I didn't say how did
they do it and then that starts
illustrating or manifesting and the
abstractions if we were using the
extract models as their sense making
structures but then that populates that
in a living way yeah I agree and I think
that there's the way that I think about
that is the usual way that things when
you trying to
you can scale it like Instagram scale
where they had 10 employees and still
had 30 million users where they scaled
through code through you know or you can
scale things through like proto examples
where you're like hey look at how these
people are doing this thing and then the
scale is just spreading that idea to
other folks it's not like the original
people that got the idea are like making
money from like everybody else doing it
or it was just like this was a good
thing looks like scale that around the
world and so I think that's a really
good perspective that I agree with yeah
I think I'd say to your question colin
is i think a lot of what you're gonna
get these new goals we talk about it
a lot is like when you think about from
like a kuhnian structure of scientific
revolutions perspective these new
paradigms and we make a new paradigm
there's like the new paradigm piece
which is one kind of science like whoa
there's a new relativity stuff or but
then there's like the normal science
within that new paradigm we're just like
how you just creating that increment
stuff so I think that a lot of what we
need to do now is like for folks like us
who are like oh man like super
pluralistic and meta modernist whatever
it's like that's cool but how do we
actually do the normal science how do
you just like make stuff actually happen
and so I think that and I can get down
to the metrics piece essentially and
that kind of gets also to this idea of
like if yeah so so that's one thing I'll
say the thing that I just agree with you
on is I think that there's you know the
supply chains and the weird like the
fact that this is both a super
connecting thing but also a very
isolating thing and how this it shows
our like lack of resilience or whatever
our just-in-time supply chain stuff and
then obviously the security and
surveillance stuff I think that would be
a those are some of the trade-offs that
we're dealing with right now it's like
okay the trade-off of Public Health is
probably good enough for the for
surveilling us to some extent and again
depending the new Bluetooth Google Apple
surveillance things are less surveilling
it than normal but so so I think that
that trade-off is definitely at hand and
we're seeing that as one of the
bifurcations for sure is like the you
know disaster capitalism versus or like
taking advantage of the crisis for money
or they're doing in Taiwan where they've
turned the trade-off between security
and our safety into an integrated
synergy where their democracy is
actually being enhanced by how they're
using AI instead of the other the ground
yeah yeah I like recently and then
there's there's an
zooom call link which I'm glad that
exists so feel free to jump on on that
so copy and paste that if you're
interested while we close yeah that was
that was awesome
reach that sparked a lot of thoughts
before I make some closing announcements
you have any closing thoughts for us I
just wanna thank everybody again for
their time and their energy and their
enthusiasm days especially but that
first thing where there was an issue
that was sad but hopefully worked out
okay and hopefully you all did some good
learning stuff if you have any other
thoughts definitely email me or put them
in that Google Doc thank you for doing
as well or if you want to help out feel
free to do that and again Peter thank
you for providing this space yeah so
I'll make some closing a coming event
announcements on upcoming events but
first three thank you so much again for
coming out I'd love to have you back and
I was thinking maybe circling
I'll see you see you and Nancy on an
email thread is that there's a wisdom
Jim emerging out of this stoic space
it'd be cool to have like a bento ism or
some something akin to that like as a
weekly basis so I'll check in with you
guys about that
so upcoming events you can check out the
website the the stoah dot CA one I'll
plug right now it's a trauma drama with
Pat Ryan it's a little bit on the dark
side but it's a I'll just leave it at
that if that intrigued you the darkness
and RSVP to it coming up next in 30
minutes is an existential dance party
you can watch a video right here you can
artists be here and the theme is
lovestruck so if you have any lovestruck
vibes romantic vibe that you want to
dance off feel free to come to that it's
gonna be the same link I'm gonna close
it down when we open up in a couple of
minutes that being said yes this is the
post capitalistic experiment of the the
stoah it's based off a gift economy I'm
viewing the stoah as a gift to the world
right now in the time of need anyone's
inspired like to provide a gift to the
stoah or me as a steward of the stoah it
has to be you know something that kind
of just bubbles up it just feels right
that delicious rightness just go to that
link for more information
that being said thanks everyone today
thank you